Chapter 1. loomings.
Call me Ishmael. Some years ago, never mind how long precisely, having little
or no money in my purse and nothing particular to interest me on shore, I
thought I would sail about a little and see the watery part of the world. It is
a way I have of driving off the spleen and regulating the circulation.
Whenever I find myself growing grim about the mouth, whenever it is a damp,
drizzly November in my soul, whenever I find myself involuntarily pausing before
coffin warehouses and bringing up the rear of every funeral I meet, and
especially whenever my hypos get such an upper hand of me, that it requires a
strong moral principle to prevent me from deliberately stepping into the
street and methodically knocking people's hats off. Then I accounted high
time to get to sea as soon as I can.
This is my substitute for pistol and ball. With a philosophical flourish, Ko
throws himself upon his sword. I quietly take to the ship. There is nothing
surprising in this. If they but knew it, almost all men in their degree sometime
or other cherish very nearly the same feelings towards the ocean with me.
There now is your insular city of the Manhatted round by warves as Indian
isles by coral reefs. Commerce surrounds it with her surf. Right and left the
streets take you waterward. Its extreme downtown is the battery where that noble
mole is washed by waves and cooled by breezes which a few hours previous were
out of sight of land. Look at the crowds of water gazers there. Circumambulate
the city of a dreamy Sabbath afternoon.
Go from Corier's Hook to Coanti's slip and from then by Whiteall northward.
What do you see? Posted like silent sentinels all around the town stand
thousands upon thousands of mortal men fixed in ocean rearies. Some leaning
against the spiles, some seated upon the peer heads, some looking over the bull
works of ships from China, some high aloft in the rigging as if striving to
get a still better seawward peep. But these are all landsmen of weekdays pent
up in lath and plaster, tied to counters, nailed to benches, clenched to
desks. How then is this? Are the green fields gone? What do they hear? But
look, here come more crowds pacing straight for the water and seemingly
bound for a dive. Strange. Nothing will content them but the extremist limit of
the land. Litering under the shady lee of yonder warehouses will not suffice.
No, they must get just as nigh the water as they possibly can without falling in.
And there they stand, miles of them, leagues. Inlanders all, they come from
lanes and alleys, streets and avenues, north, east, south, and west. Yet here
they all unite. Tell me, does the magnetic virtue of the needles of the
compasses of all those ships attract them thither?
Once more, say you are in the country, in some high land of lakes. Take almost
any path you please, and 10 to one it carries you down in a dale and leaves
you there by a pool in the stream. There is magic in it. Let the most
absent-minded of men be plunged in his deepest rearies. Stand that man on his
legs, set his feet a going, and he will infallibly lead you to water, if water
there be, in all that region. Should you ever be a thirst in the great American
desert, try this experiment if your caravan happened to be supplied with a
metaphysical professor. Yes, as everyone knows, meditation and water are wedded forever.
But here is the artist. He desires to paint you the dreamiest, shadiest,
quietest, most enchanting bit of romantic landscape in all the valley of
a sacko. What is the chief element he employs? There stand his trees, each
with a hollow trunk, as if a hermit and a crucifix were within. And here sleeps
his meadow, and there sleep his cattle, and up from yonder cottage goes a sleepy
smoke. Deep into the distant woodlands winds a mazy way, reaching to
overlapping spurs of mountains bathed in their hillside blue. But though the
picture lies thus transed, and though this pine tree shakes down its size like
leaves upon the shepherd's head, yet all were vain, unless the shepherd's eye
were fixed upon the magic stream before him. Go visit the prairies in June, when
for scores on scores of miles you weighed kneede among tiger liies. What
is the one charm wanting? Water. There is not a drop of water there. Were
Niagara but a cataract of sand, would you travel your thousand miles to see
it? Why did the poor poet of Tennessee, upon suddenly receiving two handfuls of
silver, deliberate whether to buy him a coat, which he sadly needed, or invest
the money in a pedestrian trip to Rockaway Beach? Why is almost every
robust, healthy boy with a robust, healthy soul in him at some time or
other crazy to go to sea? Why, upon your first voyage as a passenger, did you
yourself feel such a mystical vibration when first told that you and your ship
were now out of sight of land? Why did the old Persians hold the sea holy? Why
did the Greeks give it a separate deity and own brother of Jo?
Surely all of this is not without meaning. and still deeper the meaning of
that story of Narcissus, who because he could not grasp the tormenting mild
image he saw in the fountain, plunged into it and was drowned. But that same
image we ourselves see in all rivers and oceans. It is the image of the
ungraspable phantom of life, and this is the key to it all.
Now when I say I am in the habit of going to sea whenever I begin to grow
hazy about the eyes and begin to be overconscious of my lungs, I do not mean
to have it inferred that I ever go to see as a passenger. For to go as a
passenger, you must needs have a purse, and a purse is but a rag unless you have
something in it. Besides, passengers get seasick, grow quarrelome, don't sleep of
nights, do not enjoy themselves much as a general thing. No, I never go as a
passenger, nor though I am something of assault, do I ever go to see as a
commodore or a captain or a cook. I abandon the glory and distinction of
such offices to those who like them. For my part, I abominate all honorable,
respectable toils, trials, and tribulations of every kind, whatever. It
is quite as much as I can do to take care of myself without taking care of
ships, barks, brigs, schooners, and whatnot. And as for going as cook,
though I confess there is considerable glory in that, a cook being a sort of
officer on shipboard, yet somehow I never fancied broiling fowls, though
once broiled, judiciously buttered and judgically salted and peppered, there is
no one who will speak more respectfully not to say reverently of a broiled fowl
than I will. It is out of the idolatrous doting of the old Egyptians upon broiled
ibis and roasted riverhorse that you see the mummies of those creatures in their
huge bake houses, the pyramids.
No, when I go to sea, I go as a simple sailor right before the mast, plumb down
into the folks, a loft there to the royal mast head. True, they rather order
me about some and make me jump from spar to spar like a grasshopper in a May
meadow, and at first this sort of thing is unpleasant enough. It touches one's
sense of honor, particularly if you come of an old established family in the
land, the Van Wrenellers or Randolphs or Hardanutes.
And more than all, if just previous to putting your hand into the tarp pot, you
have been lording it as a country school master, making the tallest boys stand in
awe of you. The transition is a keen one, I assure you, from a school master
to a sailor, and requires a strong decoction of senica and the stoics to
enable you to grin and bear it. But even this wears off in time. What of it? If
some old hunks of a sea captain orders me to get a broom and sweep down the
decks, what does that indignity amount to, weighed, I mean, in these scales of
the New Testament? Do you think the Archangel Gabriel thinks anything the
less of me because I promptly and respectfully obey that old hunks in that
particular instance? Who ain't a slave?
Tell me that. Well then, however the old sea captains may order me about, however
they may thump and punch me about, I have the satisfaction of knowing that it
is all right, that everybody else is in one way or other served in much the same
way, either in a physical or metaphysical point of view, that is, and
so the universal thump is passed round, and all hands should rub each other's
shoulder blades and be content.
Again, I always go to sea as a sailor because they make a point of paying me
for my trouble, whereas they never pay passengers a single penny that I ever
heard of. On the contrary, passengers themselves must pay. And there is all
the difference in the world between paying and being paid. The act of paying
is perhaps the most uncomfortable infliction that the two orchard thieves
entailed upon us. But being paid, what will compare with it? The urbane
activity with which a man receives money is really marvelous, considering that we
so earnestly believe money to be the root of all earthly ills, and that on no
account can a moneyed man enter heaven.
Ah, how cheerfully we consign ourselves to predition.
Finally, I always go to see a sailor because of the wholesome exercise and
pure air of the folkal deck. For, as in this world, headwinds are far more
prevalent than winds from a stern. That is, if you never violate the Pythagorean
maxim, so for the most part, the commodore on the quarter deck gets his
atmosphere at secondhand from the sailors on the folks. He thinks he
breathes at first, but not so. In much the same way do the commonality lead
their leaders in many other things, at the same time that the leaders little
suspected. But wherefore it was that after having repeatedly smelt the sea as
a merchant sailor, I should now take it into my head to go on a whailing voyage,
this the invisible police officer of the fates, who has the constant surveillance
of me and secretly dogs me and influences me in some unaccountable way,
he can better answer than anyone else.
And doubtless my going on this whailing voyage formed part of the grand program
of providence that was drawn up a long time ago. It came as a sort of brief
interlude and solo between more extensive performances. I take it that
this part of the bill must have run something like this. Grand contested
election for the presidency of the United States. Wailing voyage by one
Ishmael. Bloody battle in Afghanistan.
Though I cannot tell why it was exactly that those stage managers, the fates put
me down for this shabby part of a wailing voyage when others were set down
for magnificent parts in high tragedies in short and easy parts in gential
comedies and jolly parts in farses.
Though I cannot tell why this was exactly, yet now that I recall all the
circumstances, I think I can see a little into the springs and motives
which, being cunningly presented to me under various disguises, induced me to
set about performing the part I did, besides cajoling me into the delusion
that it was a choice resulting from my own unbiased free will and
discriminating judgment. Chief among these motives was the overwhelming idea
of the great whale himself. Such a portentious and mysterious monster
roused all my curiosity. Then the wild and distant seas where he rolled his
island bulk, the undeliverable, the nameless perils of the whale. These,
with all the attending marvels of a thousand Patagonian sights and sounds,
helped sway me to my wish. With other men perhaps such things would not have
been inducements, but as for me, I am tormented with an everlasting itch for
things remote. I love to sail forbidden seas and land on barbarous coasts, not
ignoring what is good, I am quick to perceive a horror, and could still be
social with it, would they let me, since it is but well to be on friendly terms
with all the inmates of the place one lodges in. By reason of these things,
then the wailing voyage was welcome. The great floodgates of the wonderworld
swung open, and into the wild conceits that swayed me to my purpose, two and
two there floated into my inmost soul endless processions of the whale, and
midmost of them all one grand hooded phantom, like a snowhill in the air.